CA just put out a beefy live stream when
it comes to Total War Warhammer 40,000
that goes over a live stream of the unit
cards, the cover system, the
projectiles, battle damage, and a lot
more. Uh, so for something that was over
2 hours, I'm here to condense it down
into the key details that you need to
know. So, let's get into it. So, as
always, I have gone ahead and simplified
this down into a board with images and
notes. Uh, let's go ahead and get
started. So, at the top of this is
deployment. They covered that it's
mostly like Total War. The main
difference is that you now have the
system of reserves that we'll get into
shortly, but essentially you place your
units. It starts kind of standard on
your half of the map, but then there's
also this idea of forward deployment,
formerly known as vanguard, where some
units can go out and they can be
deployed. In this case, it's like the
caster. And so they're going to go out
there and they will allow you to uh
seize key areas and then also provide
vision. Uh they confirmed that there is
fog of war in the game. Visually, you
kind of do see this throughout the demo
in the sense that orc units kind of pop
in and out of existence, but uh they
said that uh the visuals are not in this
build. So, there'll be a greater
visibility uh of what you can and cannot
see. So, the fog will be much thicker
than is what uh you're seeing here. So,
that's cool. And then they went over
some detail on reserves and abilities.
So, the first is strategic reserves. So,
basically all armies are going to have
access to this version of strategic
reserves. The way it shows up is
different based off the faction, but
essentially where these are pulled from
is going to be dependent on the campaign
or the greater context. So you may have
reserves from the fleet or from nearby
adjacent armies. And this can go all the
way up to 40. Uh so you can deploy them
either at the start of your battle or,
you know, hot drop them into combat.
Again, it's kind of dependent on what
you want to do. The risk of deploying
them in combat is they may just take a
lot of incoming fire. So some people
like the guard might want to deploy
early. others like the space marines
might want to drop into the thick of the
combat. Uh in addition to that, they've
done a little bit of uh you know
tooling. So the balance of power bar at
the top now reflects actually both
states of readiness, not only just the
deployed troops, but then also the
strength of the reserves. So again,
showing just how strategic reserves are
going to be important and they're
overhauling everything in the UI uh to
follow. Uh one thing that I did show is
they have some cool mechanics. So
sometimes I believe reserves may walk
onto the map, but for the most part when
you deploy them, they're going to come
in. You select where they come in, and
then they might be air dropped or come
in through some sort of uh orbital drop
pod. Uh I didn't catch a glimpse for it.
I hope they show it in the future, but
I'm sure they'll have a really neat and
slick uh mechanics uh visually for that.
Uh then the other thing they went into
is down here in the UI. So this is going
to be uh your on the top is
bombardments, on the bottom is going to
be your army abilities. So, lots of
stuff to to see here. The first thing
for bombardments is obviously this is
going to be dependent on, you know, what
you've done in the campaign to unlock
these, what resources you have
available. In this case, for this
battle, they had three of them
available. So, these are going to be
off-field call-ins. Um, in this case,
there was three of them. So, there was a
godspear warheads. You can see here,
giant explosion. Then, there's a lance
strike, which comes in. This is more
about, you know, armor piercing,
knocking out big targets. A cool little
note on this one is once you deploy it,
you can actually kind of guide it like
uh Ultimate Commander or what was it?
Supreme Commander back in the day where
you could guide stuff like that. So
yeah, you can move it around which is
cool. And then the last one they showed
here is a you know a rocket pod barrage.
So presumably you can get more of these
over time once you're really advanced in
your campaign. But yeah, each of them
have their own specialties. They have
their own limited use. So if you zoom in
here, you can see that you have one uh
available currently and then they have a
cool down. Um, from what I could tell,
you know, at the start of the battle,
for instance, these are all going to be
gated on a timer. So, right when you
start, you know, you can't just nuke the
enemy. You have to wait. And then once
you do use these over time, uh, I think
there is multiple use. So, I was a
little bit confused by the numbers here.
It might be how many concurrent you have
or how many total you have. It wasn't
clear from this demo, so we'll wait.
We'll wait and see. But yeah, so that's
your bombardments. Then you have down
here, this is going to be your army
abilities. Uh, this is going to be
flavored to each faction. for the guard.
They're calling it regimental orders.
And the way this works is it's basically
orders that trickle down through the
command. They say it spreads to units
within range of command. So specific
commanders or units that may have vox
casters attached to them will be able to
collect these commands and get their
benefits. So it buffs units. Uh so in
this case, you know, take cover
increases evasion and suppression
resistance. Take aim is more offensive.
Move move uh gives you a speed buff. So
I like that. not just the flavor
particular to a faction, but the fact
that mechanically it makes sense. So,
the fact that uh the guard thing is
something that actually kind of flows
across your units and triggers through
the network of command forces through
box casters and uh leadership units. And
you can imagine when it comes to the
tyrannids, this will very much play into
the way they have their synaptic
network. So, really key to see how they
they tune this in. Uh and again, I
captured some of this. So, in the same
way that your bombardments have cool
downs, same thing with your orders. So
after this move move, it looked like it
was about a 40 second cool down after
the click. And again, you'd imagine in
the campaign you can tweak the cooldown
period of these by going down different
lines of uh of specialization. So yeah,
that's going to be sort of deployment
and then using abilities. Uh then they
did a pretty deep dive on the unit cards
themselves. So a lot to go over here and
I have to tell you this is more than I
could have imagined. Uh and it has a lot
of implications for historical uh titles
in the future, specifically Medieval 3.
Uh so let's look at this. So, first off,
what are we looking at? So, they zoomed
in on a particular unit. You can click
on the card and then here's the card
here. Lots of information that we'll get
into, but at a high level, you have kind
of your overview of your unit.
Obviously, the stuff we're used to, the
title, the type, you get the the count
of the troops. You have some key stats
about them. So, firepower is simplified
into just light uh unit classes, medium
and heavy. So, they went over that.
Light would be something that's lots of
units with low armor. Medium is a less
amount of units with medium amount of
armor. And heavy is going to be stuff
like tanks or stuff that are very low
unit count but heavily armored. Um, so
yeah, a quick view to see how your unit
reacts to that. And then you can also
see what uh different quick uh little
pieces of equipment you have attached to
that unit. And each of those will kind
of trickle up. And let's say for
instance, you have a lot more plasma
specialists and plasma guns in your
unit. It'll increase your ability to
take on medium uh targets or even heavy
targets. So, all of this is dynamic. I
got some quick screen grabs of these.
So, if you mouse over them, you get some
details. So, las gun here, laser cuts
through enemy targets with high energy
bolts, a focus light, it gives you the
range, and there's swap conditions,
which is key. We'll get into that
shortly. Uh, but then, yeah, so key here
is going to be you have a bunch of
equipment, and they all have different
benefits. Even grenades are thrown in
the mix. Uh, so how does this all play
out? We'll get into that in just a
second, but first I wanted to kind of
wrap up the rest of the stats. Uh, the
other thing here, you can hit this plus
to get an expanded view and then you can
look at more stats for your unit. This
is the boil down version of it. So
again, stuff we're used to, armor,
damage, resistance, makes sense. Evasion
is specifically how much you can reduce
the accuracy of incoming uh, weapons
firing at range. And then this gets
buffed by cover. You can see here
evasion is way way up in this case
because of the fact that this unit was
in cover. And then defense more
specifically is defense against melee
attacks. Charge defense, max speed,
charge speed. Those are things we're
familiar with. So wanted to go over
that. And then yeah, there's other stuff
in the unit card. All sorts of different
conditions like moving, taking fire,
heavy flanking, suppression. We'll go
over that later. But just suffice to
say, they gave us the whole treatment of
showing everything in the unit cards.
Okay. Now, specifically to the unit
cards and how they bellay sort of this
underlying principle of the the mixed
bag of what is actually in a unit, which
is really interesting. So, in this case,
uh again, basic view. So, you can you'll
click on your caster, there's 30 troops
within it, and it gives you a summary of
your kind of power of versus light
versus medium versus heavy units. And
this is all uh representative of again
the kit that you have on your squad. So,
if you want to know what is impacting
this, you can hit expand and then you
can start to cycle through your weapons.
The first thing if you go on this first
button here which is overall you get a
summary of well what is in my unit. So
this is really cool. So at the top this
is representative of the different
constituent bits of soldiers within your
squad. So clicking on them for instance
you would say that the first one says oh
of my total 30 units. 16 are basic
casterins. Two are vox casters. Two are
sergeants and 10 are specialists. And
then you can increase that over time.
You can swap it out. But it's really
cool. It's live. It's dynamic. Um, so
for instance, let's say that your unit
gets hit by a grenade. That grenade can
actually take out all of your
specialists and all of a sudden that
will be reflected. Your specialist here
will drop to zero and then the traits
that they are otherwise enabling your
unit to have. That would reduce the
effectiveness of your overall unit. So,
super dynamic stuff that I'm really
excited about. So, yeah, entities within
a unit can have their own stats. They
can have their own gear. You can have
psykers embedded in your unit that are
popping off their abilities, but are
otherwise tied to the overall unit. Um,
soldiers also have multiple weapons that
they can um, bring to bear and they'll
swap between primary and secondary uh,
weapons based off context. So in this
case they're saying that hey caster's
mostly they're using their las gun, but
they may be able to pull out a crack
grenade or something. And uh, I believe
in some cases it may be an active
ability, but in most cases they say that
these grenades and these secondary
weapons like flamers are things that the
unit will automatically do based off
context. So, for instance, if an armored
foe comes upon them, they're going to
try and use anti-armour weaponry. Or if
they're fighting units in cover, the
flamers will start to use that when it's
appropriate, when they're in range and
stuff like that. So, that's really cool.
Uh, and in terms of how customizable you
can make this, uh, they're saying that
these sort of specialist and these
tweaks that you make to your unit, they
don't want it to be crazy. So, like
overall, your caskin should stay like,
you know, a battleline infantry. And
yes, you can maybe tweak the stats up to
like 20%ish, but you shouldn't be able
to turn them into space marines with all
these upgrades. So, it gives you flavor,
but within a degree. And then here is
some examples that they showed later of
kind of the specialist kind of secondary
uh effects that your troops can have.
So, in this case, organically, Soldier
decided to throw a crack grenade. Uh,
and in this case, flamers decided to
engage units in cover when they were
within range. So, I really like that.
Uh, and then here we show off some
specific units. So again, this unicard
system is super detailed. So uh over
here, you know, you could this is on the
overall, but if you click on a specific
weapon like the las gun or whatever, you
can see it here. If I click on the las
gun, I get specific stats on the las
gun. What is the weapons profile of that
las gun? So you get a super detail of
like what does this weapon do? And then
it tells you at the top how many units
are equipped with that. So in this case,
16 of my caster have the las gun. Uh 16
of them also have frag grenades. If I
keep going on, uh, here, I only have 10
specialists in the squad. If I click on
the plasma gun, those go to the
specialists. Presumably, maybe there's
units that could have multiple, you
know, maybe you have different types of
specialists and they could both have
plasma. So, anyways, it's it's a really
dynamic way to show this. Uh, and then,
you know, later when it comes to like
your sergeants and your leaders, they
have specific weapons like chains, last
pistols. So, I really like this. The
fact that you can kit out individual
units and have that kind of trickle up
to the highest level and have units
dynamically swap between them is
incredible in terms of modeling, you
know, accuracy to the tabletop and then
modeling closer to how real world
situations work. And especially for me
for historical, this has great benefits
when it comes to medieval warfare and
any historical warfare. Swapping between
primary secondary weapons, having mixed
weapons units is just incredible. Uh,
and then lastly here, I did want to show
off one of the main bodyguard units. So,
they did confirm that, hey, most
characters, you know, your heroes, you
know, this is what you would expect in
other Total War titles are going to be
standalone. Uh, in this case, most
characters do have bodyguards, which
would work in a similar fashion where
you can click on the commasar, see their
stats, but then otherwise, the rest of
the unit has that same sort of system we
were just talking about. Uh, but there
are some cases where very powerful units
or if the conditions are right, it could
just be one character has one entity and
that would be your unit. So probably
that's going to be giant bosses. I don't
know if they're doing primarks, but they
would be single entities. Same as like
maybe a chapter master or definitely
some of the orc bosses or the tyrannid
monsters. So yeah, we can expect a mix
of those two. So that's unit cards.
Again, it blays a lot of depth that
they're adding and reworking to the
system of how units behave and how kind
of eclectic they are. And that is great.
It's enabled by the new engine and it'll
carry over to all the historical titles.
Very exciting. Uh, next we get into kind
of the meat of well, this is all about
range combat. You know, there's melee
thrown in, but basically everyone is
going to be shooting each other in Total
War Warhammer 40,000. So, this is key.
So, they spent a huge chunk of this
presentation talking about the cover
system and the projectiles. So we'll go
ahead and start with cover. So the first
thing to note about cover is they said
that there are different types of cover
naturally. So there's light cover which
they said would be things like trees or
vegetation or little small scrubs and
things like that. And then there is
heavy cover. Heavy cover would be
something like you're seeing here, imp
placements, things that are, you know,
have weight, concrete, sandbags,
buildings, things like that. Uh and then
there uh are also even emergent versions
of cover. So they said that there's like
for instance when an explosion goes off
it'll leave behind a crater. This is an
emergent type of cover. Uh then these
different types of cover have different
levels of effectiveness. So this is
based off both simulated uh projectiles.
So like the shape of the cover will
impact the simulated path of a
projectile and how much it actually
blocks incoming fire. So um the
effectiveness of cover is based off
actual simulation. But then Creative
Assembly knows that um that can get
gimmicky and finicky. And so in addition
to that, there's an additional buff
that's you just get for being in cover
regardless of what the simulation says.
So you'll get some evasion bonus to
being in cover. And um that buff will
actually be persistent even if cover is
destroyed and it's no longer there
because a tank rolled over it. CI
doesn't want cover to be eliminated
entirely. It's still relevant. That
rubble still has some value in the
battlefield. And so even if cover is
destroyed, you still get the buff of the
area, although it'll be somewhat
reduced. So I like that, the fact that
they're not doing away with it and the
fact that they're having some redundancy
in case the kind of projectile based
calculations end up being wonky. So I
like that. Uh they did mention also that
some projectiles can penetrate through
cover. Um you know, flamers, for
instance, might ignore cover. Uh
defense, things like that. Maybe plasma
can shoot through certain cover. Um so
yeah, it's all really cool. Uh and then
yeah, the last thing they did mention is
that the sort of emergent cover like
these craters uh will get simulated
cover, but they do not get the buff. So
that buff based version of cover is only
for the pre-place stuff that exists on
the battlefield at the start of combat.
Uh and then yeah, they showed off some
more stuff. So they had bombardments
that came in. They showed a cool kind of
destruction sequence as it blew up
cover. This is something they've been
touting for the engine where obviously
strategically you want to eliminate
cover to make it easier to target the
foe. So they've been showing a lot of
that. Uh and then yeah specifically you
can target cover using um you know
orbital call-ins and big bombardments
but you can also do it using units. In
this case they showed that yes las guns
can try and shoot cover. It'll take a
time uh tanks can shoot it and it goes
much quicker. So you know all layers of
depth and strategy. Uh they then had a
series of kind of cover demos showing
different units engaging. Uh and we'll
get into this shortly, but I'll just
play some clips here. Um it's all very
good. It looks realistic to me. It's it
the behavior feels very natural and
yeah, very much appreciated. Uh so yeah,
now let's get into the projectiles. So
projectiles. So one of the things they
said is that um they're changing sort of
how projectiles work. The first thing is
that they recognize that moving into
this title is there's just going to be a
lot more projectiles flying across the
battlefield than any other Total War
title. So they've done some changes to
sort of the engine such that the usual
physics tick rate that calculates when
projectiles leave where they are.
They've actually increased that
dramatically. So they have a much better
capability of modeling uh projectiles,
especially high uh rate of fire
projectiles. They said uh specifically
every projectile is real. So, they've
always said that in the past, but maybe
they faked it. They said, "Here, no
smoke and mirrors. Everything is real."
And one of the things that people asked
in the chat was, "Hey, I'm seeing as you
know, this projectile is going off. I'm
seeing some ricochets." The question
was, "Do you actually model the
ricochet? And can that can that do
damage?" So, the answer is no. Ricochets
are visual only, but they're indications
of kind of armor bounces and kind of
deflecting damage. So, ricochets are
there, but you can't get hit and killed
by a ricocheted bullet.
Uh, and then they talked some behind the
hood or under the hood mechanics for
projectiles. A lot more stuff controls
it. Rate of fire, aim time delay, reload
speed, mid- burst delay, burst size,
burst per magazine, all sorts of stuff
that really makes it, you know, it's
it's a clear overhaul to how they're
doing projectiles. Uh, another cool
thing as part of the overhaul is sort of
the firing cycle inherent in particular
units. I thought this was really uh,
interesting. So this informs both the
animation and the simulation. And the
way they worked is basically let's say
we zoom in on an individual guardsman.
They're actually going through their own
cycle of firing and reloading. So the
way it works is first that unit will
seek to acquire a target. It decides it
wants to engage with it. It will then go
aim and zero in. So that's an actual
animation and it's an actual calculation
in the physics. Then it will shoot.
It'll keep shooting and as it shoots
there may be some delay. So that's due
to recoil. So, let's say you're firing a
gun that maybe shoots and then it's a
half second before you can shoot again.
They model that versus a machine gun
will have a lot of shoots before it has
that delay. So, that's something they
can tweak on a per unit or sorry, per
weapon basis, which is really cool. And
then what happens is that unit will keep
shooting. And what's really cool here is
they shoot until they have to reload.
So, there's this concept of actually
having magazine capacities and things
like that based on different units. So,
I I really like that. And that's
individualled all the way modeled all
the way down to the individual level. So
that cycle will repeat. And a cool thing
is they said this cycle of kind of shoot
until you have to reload can be
interrupted. So for instance, they gave
an example. Let's say a guardsman is
shooting, you know, 25% of his mag. You
tell him to move. Once he starts
shooting again, uh, he has 75% of his
ammo left because he had already shot.
So, they're emphasizing that this is
tracked on a per model level regardless
of where they go in the battlefield.
That's crazy level of details. That's
really interesting. Uh, there was a
question in chat which says, "Okay, but
what if a guardsman is sitting idle?
Will he actually go ahead and reload
back to 100%." And they said that's kind
of a work in progress, but I like the
ability. I I just like the fact that
they're tracking like magazine
capacities on individual soldiers within
units within an entire battlefield.
Crazy stuff.
Uh and then key to projectiles is
obviously line of sight. Once a
projectile lose uh you know leaves a
particular gun, where does it go? So um
yeah, they talked about this. So they
said overall when it comes to like a
unit and it firing, they said first
shape of that unit matters. This is you
know important for uh you know
Napoleonic warfare or whatever. How much
frontage versus depth you have is how
much you can fire. Obviously the wider
your unit is the more units are up
front, the more they can shoot. So that
is present in this game, but they're
trying to make it a bit more dynamic. So
it's not functioning just like you know
lines of battle from Napoleonic ages. Uh
but still that that it's a you can't get
away from it. Even with modern units,
the more spread out you are, the more
you can fire. So yeah, they have that.
Uh and the way it works basically for
this is there's calculation for units
willingness to fire through friendlies.
So basically, if you have something
that's like, let's say, a square, the
first couple ranks will shoot freely,
and then the further and further back
you get, the more hesitant they are to
shoot through their soldiers. But in
order to prevent this from being
something like Napoleonic Warfare, they
are actually allowing those units in the
back to choose other targets. So let's
say you have units on your flank, those
soldiers in the back can actually shoot
in the flank. Or if you have units in
the back, they can shoot in the back.
So, an individual unit placed in one
location might have a primary facing,
but they can actually shoot 360. So,
that's really cool. Um, and then they
said there is going to be some
tolerance, a little bit of buffer in
there so that if units are right next to
cover, previously it was janky where
players would get frustrated if it's
like, you know, I think I can shoot, but
technically there's a pixel there so
they won't. They're going to allow a
little bit of tolerance so you can kind
of shoot through cover or kind of have a
little bit more allowance to get past
that sort of player frustration that has
plagued uh recent titles. So glad to see
they're working on that. And then
finally, they're trying to make it more
uh visibly present or visibly obvious
when line of sight is broken. So when
you target individual units, so you can
see here, there are going to be like
these little sighteline lasers that
trace from where you're shooting to
where you're trying to shoot. And if
it's green, that means you're all clear
to shoot. And I think they said that if
there is some sort of obstacle blocking
your way, it'll appear red or it'll
appear discontinued or they're going to
try and make it obvious that hey, line
of sight is broken. So, I like that. Um,
both having sort of the modeling ability
to to make it actually matter when cover
is there, but then giving the player the
ability to understand uh when they might
otherwise be frustrated by a lack of
information. So, I like that. Uh, more
stuff about firing. They did say when
you're engaged in combat. So, for
instance, here in the demo, they had
some ogrin tearing up some uh troops in
close quarters. They said, "Hey, units
on both sides as they're engaged in
close quarters, the individual soldiers
will determine whether or not they're
actually in combat. Cue the combat
animations or if they're in the back of
the unit of either the attacker or the
defender, they will keep firing as well.
So, yeah, all of that is really cool.
So, you can still fire while in combat."
Uh, another key things is this fire and
maneuver. So they said they wanted again
to break away from this idea of
Napoleonic warfare in order to get
something where you can move and
organically keep shooting as you're
repositioning. So they've been throwing
around the term strafing which basically
lets you move around and keep firing as
you do so. Uh they basically said
everyone can fire and move but as you do
so you will suffer some penalties. So
they showed a tank pulling back while
still firing ahead and it sponsor kind
of shooting. Same thing here in these
shots. there were ogen and guard units
pulling back, walking slowly while
firing. Same thing with these sentinels.
Now, they did say in early testing, uh,
basically this was a meta. Everyone ran
into battle and then it was basically
who can walk back the most and fire. So,
in order to prevent that, they actually
uh did some debuffs. So, yes, you can
fire while moving, but there's penalties
for doing so. So, that'll debuff
accuracy, it might debuff damage, it
might have other debuffs. Um, and this
is, you know, there's different units
that might be better than others at this
type of strafing maneuvers. Orcs not
very good. Yes, they might want to run
and charge, but the more they do so, the
more they're going to fire wildly.
Guardsmen might be decent, and space
marines would be excellent. They can
fire maneuver without losing any
accuracy. So, you know, that'll add more
flavor to the units. Uh, last couple
thing that they showed is elevation does
matter. So again, they're doing a
combination of simulated benefits and
then actually kind of uh stat benefits.
So simulated benefits is basically as
you're looking at these two units and
they're trying to target each other.
Obviously if you're at a higher
elevation, you can according to the
physics engine shoot over cover and hit
your opponent. So that's one benefit.
But then they also are going to be
calculating bonuses on the back end
based off relative height difference to
give you stat bonuses to compensate for
maybe again some wonkiness of the the
physics engine. and they showed some
examples of that at different levels of
kind of severity. And yes, you could see
that it definitely had an impact.
Uh, another thing they did is kind of
changing up how uh unit targeting works.
So, in past or recent Total War titles,
uh, when you have artillery targeting a
unit, often there would be this issue
where it targets the corner and you're
just not getting getting effective fire
across the entire unit. So, they've
started to fix that. So now uh tanks
they showed engaging against an orc unit
will actually engage the entire orc
unit. Strafe it, fire, spray it back and
forth and do everything. And they said,
you know, this is something they're
rolling out across multiple units is
that um individual units can split fire
target. So you may tell a unit to target
a primary force. Um, but units in the
back who are otherwise unengaged or
can't engage with that target will
actually start to shoot at other targets
nearby and in the vicinity and spread
their fire across a particular unit. So
again, this is all really, really good
stuff that I'm excited to see. Um, yeah,
then we go into some more stuff about
unit behavior, suppression, flanking,
and battle damage. So unit behavior,
this is one of the cool things that they
did highlight. So speaking of kind of
how units engage with each other when it
comes to projectiles, they have very
specific modes. So, one of them is
sentry. Sentry is really slick.
Essentially, what it is is you activate
it and essentially your unit will uh
it's well, I'll just read it here.
Selected units will not move to attack a
range target if they are out of range.
Instead, they will mark the target and
prioritize shooting at it when it comes
into range. So, essentially, this lets
you designate target priority. So, let's
say that you put all your guardsmen into
like a city or a building, whatever.
They're going to keep fending off little
attacks that might come to them, but you
can target an enemy boss that's
lingering off in the distance, and the
second that boss comes in range, they're
now going to switch their fire onto that
target. So, sentry mode is really cool.
I I like that ability. Uh flagging
particular units that you want to fight,
but not having that come at the expense
of fending off other units who might be
engaging with you. So, I really like
that, and I'm sure they'll have
different behavior modes in the future.
Uh more kind of unit specific stuff.
when they're in combat, you have
suppression. So, suppression works as
expected. Uh, and there's a little popup
that shows up on top of a unit, light
suppression, heavy suppression. And
basically what it does is it debuffs
your movement speed and it slows down
your rate of fire. And different units
may or may not care about being
suppressed or may be otherwise immune to
it. So, a big tank or a big space marine
unit or something may not, you know,
they'll shrug off a lot of small arms
fire uh versus others might be more
susceptible to it. Uh, other stuff that
they are talking about is flanking.
So we talked about here well units can
kind of fire in all directions but still
there is the this idea of a unit
generally speaking is still facing one
direction and therefore you have side
flanks rear flanks especially for
vehicles you can imagine so it is still
key to be flanked and what does that
mean? So you'll see these little
overheads that appear. So in this case
there was a orc unit coming around
behind this guard position. It started
off as light flanking and then as they
kind of enveloped into this position and
were on top of them, that light flanking
warning turned into heavy flanking. Uh,
same thing can occur to vehicles. You
can see here, I believe it's one of the
stompas moving forward and yep, you can
see a guard unit on its flank. The
vehicle now takes a light flanking
penalty. So, what does this do? Well, as
in past Total War titles, flanking
impacts morale, but it can also do more
dam damage, especially when it comes to
vehicles. if you get around the flank or
the the wherever its main frontal armor
is, you can do more damage, especially
in the rear. So, yeah, like to see it.
Uh, and then lastly here, they went over
a little bit more stuff when it comes to
battle damage over the course of
prolonged action. So, one cool thing
when it comes to battle damage is they
have this concept of uh chaotic deaths.
Oh, sorry, that's a little typo there.
Uh, so chaotic deaths. And essentially
what that is is basically, you know,
we're used to total war units dying and
having death animations, but there is a
percentage chance that said unit may
have a very violent or chaotic death.
And I really like that. And so they had
one example of a storm boy force which,
you know, took a bunch of hits, it
exploded, and there's a, you know,
standard explosion animation. But one of
them in particular had a storm boy
flying up in the screen going across
almost like a mile away and crash
landing somewhere else. And the cool
thing about that is they can, you know,
tailor it to specific units to have
really interesting chaotic stuff. Like
if a tank explodes, maybe a chaotic
thing will be it doesn't just die there,
but maybe it can go out of control and
keep running around, running over units,
and then exploding somewhere else. So, I
like this idea of chaotic death adds
more visual flavor and it can be very
40k and then it can have impacts on the
battlefield when it comes to splash
damage or unintended consequences. Uh,
and then the last thing that I thought
was really cool was after the battle,
they replayed it multiple times and they
showed off the battle damage. Some some
really slick uh, you know, shots of the
battlefield here. It looks posed. It
looks like something you'd see in a game
where everyone handpicked meticulously
to make an epic scene. This was just a
random area that they zoomed in on. So,
you could see, yeah, just the carnage
left over from Battlefields is beautiful
in and of itself. But then they're also
doing sort of that battle damage be
reflected on individual units, which is
really cool. So they zoomed in on this
and basically what'll happen is as your
units take different types of damage
it'll actually be reflected on that
unit. So uh and not just that but it
depends on what types of damage they
were taking. So they showed like the
bane blade for instance if it took a lot
of small arms fire it'll have little
bullet holes in it. If it was taking
flamer damage it'll have scorch marks.
Same thing with plasma and other stuff
like that. So it's not just how much
damage you took but what type of damage
you took. And so it's very visible on
tanks, less vis less visible on a
squishy unit like guardsman because
they'll just die. Um, but let's say you
had one of these guardsman that are
alive. They specifically mentioned I
think they had a commaar who took flamer
damage and at the end of the battle he
survived but he was like completely
scorched. So a lot of these little hero
moments that tell a visual story uh I
thought was really cool. Uh and then
yeah more just brutality of the
battlefield after the fact. It's just
looking great.
Uh, and then a final little mention they
had here is the optimization of course
was a little bit janky in this
playthrough and that's something that
people have remarked upon. CA said that
hey, you know, the build that we're
seeing is not the latest build and even
the latest build is still going through
a lot of work to have optimization.
They're pushing that as a huge focus and
yeah, they're going to keep to improve
right up until launch and obviously post
launch. But you could see with just the
amount of detail that they're adding to
the game, I could see why it struggles
when you talk about the intricacies of
the cover system, the projectiles, the
modeling you're doing for all the units
of what gear are they using, what, you
know, what is the individual capacity in
their magazine, where are they in their
firing cycle? It's just a crazy amount
of stuff. And so the fact that CA is
seemingly being able to pull this off
has me very excited for not only 40,000,
but imagine pivoting all this into
something like Medieval 3. Same engine,
same proof of concept. 40K is paying the
big bucks for the R&D and then we can
leverage that for Medieval for an
awesome game. So yeah, seeing this
future looks bright for Total Warhammer
uh and other titles in the future. So
yeah, stay tuned for more. We'll be
seeing a lot more live streams shortly.
And uh as always, I'll try and break it
down. And stay tuned for more history
documentaries. We got a lot of those
cooking. See you.